I do as they tell me
and the street is safe.
Who are they?
I never meant for anyone to get hurt.
(RAVEN CROWING)
(WHISPERS) Let me be brave.
Is it a trap? Is it a torture chamber?
If you were any part of killing her
and you're not afraid.
then you understand nothing at all.
(ICE CRACKS)
DOCTOR: Go to the city.
Tell them I'm back.
Tell them I know what they did.
(MUSIC PLAYING OVER RADIO)
(DOOR CLOSES)
♪ Don't stop me now
♪ I'm having such a good time
♪ I'm having a ball ♪
Hi.
What can I get you?
I don't have any money.
But I play.
Okay.
Don't you need to plug that thing in?
Yeah.
(GLASSES WHIRRING)
You're English.
You're not?
How did you get out here?
Magic.
Or maybe I went to an airport
and caught a plane.
- Ah. (CHUCKLES)
- You?
Magic.
(RADIO CRACKLES)
I believe you.
- You been travelling?
- Yeah.
From time to time.
Is it a sad song?
Nothing's sad till it's over.
Then everything is.
What's it called?
I think that it's called...
Clara.
Tell me about her.
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
Ripped By mstoll
Happy New Year 2016 - New Year. New Color ;-)
(WIND WHISTLING)
(BELLS TOLLING)
Lord President.
Are all the bells ringing?
The whole Cloister?
What's going on down there?
(BELLS TOLLING)
GASTRON: I'm on my way
down to the Matrix now. sir.
GENERAL: Keep the perimeter.
It's okay to be afraid
down there. soldier.
Sliders are everywhere. sir.
Loads of those things.
GENERAL: Language. please.
I'm with the President.
Sorry. sir.
The Cloister Wraiths are active.
Do not approach them. Don't even
enter the Cloister. just tell me.
Are all the bells ringing?
Yes. sir.
Then we are facing great danger.
The Cloister Wraiths seem to think so.
So where is he?
Where has the Doctor gone?
Back to the beginning. I should think.
The Sisterhood of Karn has
no business in this chamber
or on this planet.
I heard the Doctor had come home.
One so loves fireworks.
(SCOFFS)
(BELLS TOLLING IN DISTANCE)
Why are they ringing all the bells?
Never heard so many.
What's gone wrong this time?
All the fuss they're always making.
You up there.
You're not supposed to be there.
I've only just put all that back.
it's for the boys.
If any of them ever want to come...
They'll kill you.
(SPOON TINKLES)
(SPACECRAFT APPROACHING)
GASTRON ON PA: Attention.
Will all non-military personnel
step away from the Doctor.
I repeat.
All non-military personnel.
please step away from the Doctor.
At least move the children away.
Doctor. you lay down
any weapons on your person
and accompany us to the Capitol.
Doctor. you will
accompany us to the Capitol.
Doctor?
Come back.
You will come back. immediately.
That is an order.
Ana' this is a military vehicle.
What's his plan?
I think he's finishing his soup.
- Suggestion. sir.
- Mmm.
GENERAL: We could talk to him.
PRESIDENT: Words are his weapons.
GENERAL:
When did they stop being ours?
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
Welcome home. sir.
As commander of the
armed forces of Gallifrey.
I bring you the greetings
of the High Council.
Who the hell does he think he is?
The man who won the Time War. sir.
(KNOCK ON DOOR)
(DOOR SLAMS SHUT)
What is he doing?
What does he want?
Revenge?
The Doctor does not blame Gallifrey
for the horrors of the Time War.
I should hope not.
He just blames you.
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
(BREATHING SHAKILY)
Get off my planet.
We needed to know.
You have information about the Hybrid.
a danger to all of us.
If you told us what you knew.
you could have walked out of there.
Get off my planet.
You have nothing. Doctor. Nothing!
Do you know what I have out here.
in the dry lands.
where there's nobody who matters?
No witnesses.
Me. too.
Take aim!
Aim at the Doctor.
- Fire on my command.
- Sir?
PRESIDENT: Step forward and take aim!
What's the matter with you?
Lord President. he's a war hero.
Some of these men served with him.
These men serve me!
All of you!
(GUNS POWERING UP)
On my command.
Fire!
DOCTOR: Could I have a lemonade?
Oh. You like a cliffhanger. don't you?
So. you went back to your hometown.
Something like that.
Glasgow?
Uh... Well. sort of Glasgow.
Space Glasgow.
And there's this gang boss
and he wanted to kill you?
Wanted to. Yeah.
You missed.
All of you. Every single one of you.
How is that possible?
What is it?
Is the firing squad afraid
of the unarmed man?
You. explain.
There was a saying. sir.
in the Time War.
A saying?
GASTRON: First thing you notice
about the Doctor of War
is he's unarmed.
For many. it's also the last.
I was at Skull Moon. sir.
Is this a story
or did this really happen?
Every story I ever told really happened.
Stories
are where memories go
when they're forgotten.
Not one more of you moves.
That is an order.
A direct order of your president!
You leave me no choice.
How many regenerations did we grant you?
- I've got all night.
- (SPACECRAFTS APPROACHING)
Excellent. General.
you sent for reinforcements.
DOCTOR: No. he didn't.
I did.
I am Rassilon. the redeemer.
Rassilon. the resurrected.
Gallifrey is mine!
Lord President. with respect.
get off his planet.
GENERAL: Gallifrey is
currently positioned
at the extreme end of the time continuum
for its own protection.
We're the end of the Universe.
give or take a star system.
I know. I came the long way around.
The President may not
find anywhere to go.
He's not the president any more.
He was a good man once.
Isn't this going a little far?
Oh. I've barely started.
Tell the High Council
they're on the next shuttle.
OHILA: I thought I'd
find you down here. Old times.
You're a long way from Karn.
At the end of everything. one must
expect the company of immortals.
Do you know what they did to me?
Confession dial is a ritual act
of purification.
It allows a dying Time Lord
to face his demons and make his peace.
before his mind
is uploaded to the Matrix.
It was never intended
as a torture chamber for the living!
Rassilon grew concerned about
the coming of the Hybrid.
Afraid.
You were entrapped
and imprisoned at his command.
- And look at him now.
- Why did you banish him?
Was it punishment.
or for your own protection?
Were you just being cruel
or just being cowardly?
Let's see. shall we?
If you wanted to know about the Hybrid.
why didn't you just ask me?
If the Hybrid is a threat
to the people of this world.
why don't you just tell us?
What do you know already?
- The Hybrid is a legendary...
- No.
The Hybrid is a creature thought to be
crossbred from two warrior races.
Which races?
The Daleks and the Time Lords.
It is supposed...
Oh. it must be well hard then.
Unstoppable. according to the stories.
If they're just stories.
why are you so worried?
Some Matrix prophecies suggest...
No.
Many prophecies suggest...
All Matrix prophecies concur
that this creature will one day
stand in the ruins of Gallifrey.
It will unravel the web of time
and destroy a billion billion
hearts to heal his own.
What colour is it?
I don't know.
These prophecies. they never tell
you anything useful. do they?
This is no time to play the fool.
It's the end of the Universe.
it's the only time I've got!
And you want me to keep you all safe?
- Can you?
- I'll need help. obviously.
Gallifrey is at your command.
Well. not from you lot.
No. you'd cramp my style.
Look at your hats.
I'm going to need the use
of an extraction chamber
to talk to an old friend.
(RAVEN CROWING)
(WHISPERS) Let me be brave.
(THUD)
(EXHALES SHARPLY)
This way. I can save you.
- Doctor?
- DOCTOR: Yeah.
Where am I? Is this the Tardis?
DOCTOR: No. this is a planet.
CLARA: What planet?
- Basically. my place.
- I was about to die.
I should be dead.
DOCTOR: Forget about that.
It doesn't matter.
- Hang on. Your place?
- Yeah.
- What do you mean your place?
- My place.
- CLARA: You don't mean...
- Yeah.
Gallifrey.
Okay. Uh... Hang on. Wait. What?
What? Did I miss something?
Well. we're several billion
years in the future
and the universe is pretty much over.
so. yeah. quite a lot.
GENERAL: Young lady. Miss Oswald.
I'm afraid we only have
a very few minutes with you.
Who's he?
According to the Doctor.
you can tell us something
about the creature known as the Hybrid.
Ah. Ooh.
Well. that's weird.
What's wrong with my ears?
- DOCTOR: Nothing.
- Ooh.
It's weird. Everything sounds wrong.
- DOCTOR: It's a side effect.
- I can hear you.
- I can hear you fine.
- DOCTOR: Uh-huh.
But I don't know. It's like. um...
It's like something's missing.
Doctor. we have to tell her.
We always tell them.
Tell me what?
What's he talking about? Doctor?
Doctor. what's going on?
DOCTOR: Clara. there's a sound
you've been living with
every day of your life.
that you've learnt not to hear.
What sound?
What's wrong? just tell me.
Doctor. what sound?
Your heartbeat.
Your physical processes
have been time looped.
Frozen between one heartbeat
and the next.
Even your breathing is just a habit.
You don't need it.
If I'm frozen. how can I...
How can I be walking about?
Because the Time Lords are very clever.
- It doesn't matter...
- Yes. it matters to me.
Doctor. we have to explain.
Doctor. what is going on?
GENERAL: Although you are
currently conscious and aware.
in fact. you died billions of years ago.
Doctor?
We have extracted you at the
very end of your time stream
to request your help.
Once we're finished here. you'll be
returned to your final moments.
Your death is an
established historical event
and cannot be altered. I'm sorry.
Doctor. will you just talk to me?
I'll try not to break your jaw.
- My jaw?
- I wasn't talking to you.
(GRUNTS)
Doctor. you can't do this.
You know you can't.
No. General. I don't know that.
Everybody. stay exactly where you are.
No moving about.
On pain of death. no one take a selfie.
These people are unarmed.
So are you.
Doctor. I will not let you leave here.
That's the sidearm
of the president's personal security.
There isn't a stun setting.
I will not let Clara die.
She's been dead
for half the lifetime of the universe.
If you try to change that.
you could fracture time itself.
Doctor. Lord President.
are you really gonna take that risk?
Doctor.
Please.
I don't want this.
Put it down. please.
Regeneration.
Death.
Good luck.
- You too. sir.
- (GUNSHOT)
I want a neural block.
Human compatible. Quickly. come on.
Come on. Quick!
This Clara person.
you must really like her.
Why do you say that?
You killed a man.
You don't seem the type.
CLARA: You killed that man.
You shot him. He's dead.
- DOCTOR: It was him or you.
- I don't care!
Yeah? Well. the difference is.
when you die. you stay dead.
So does he.
We're on Gallifrey.
Death is Time Lord for man flu.
Med Team to Sector 52.
extraction chamber seven.
Regeneration in progress.
Are you all right. sir?
(STUTTERS) Uh. sorry. ma'am.
(GRUNTS)
Back to normal. am I?
The only time I've been a man.
that last body.
Dear Lord. how do you
cope with all that ego?
Ma'am. where's the Doctor?
The Cloisters. Where else would he run?
Except into the greatest
danger on Gallifrey.
The hell of the Time Lords.
I thought you said Gallifrey was frozen
in another dimension.
Well. they must have unfrozen it
and come back.
CLARA: How?
I didn't ask.
It'd make them feel clever.
Happy?
- No.
Tell me what a neural block is.
DOCTOR: Never mind.
This way.
CLARA: What did you mean.
human compatible?
So. what was it. the thing you took?
There was only one way
to keep Clara safe.
I had to wipe some of her memory.
Of what?
Of me.
The Cloister Wraiths.
Sliders. we used to call them.
They guard the Matrix.
- We're safe here.
- Why?
They only attack
if you make any attempt to leave.
How long are we planning to stay?
Or actually. if you try to stay.
You realise how well that
conversation went. right?
I'm starting to. yeah. a bit.
(EERIE HOWLING)
FEMALE GENERAL: We need to block
every exit from the Cloisters.
Every available man.
I need that place surrounded.
No one's ever made it
back out of the Cloisters.
No quite no one.
DOCTOR: This way. I'm fairly sure.
According to the stories.
there's a secret way out.
If you find it. the Sliders let you go.
DALEK: Exterminate.
It's okay. It's okay. Look at it.
Exterminate me.
Is it trapped?
DOCTOR: Don't worry.
it's been neutralised.
Those aren't vines.
In your terms. they are fibre optic
cables. they're alive and growing.
We're inside the
biggest database in history.
Sometimes. people are
stupid enough to break in.
And?
It's a database. They get filed.
Exterminate...
...me.
Probably left over
from the Cloister Wars.
There's nothing we can do.
Come on.
Exterminate me!
(CLARA GASPS)
Keep away from them.
The Matrix can use them as a defence.
It means the secret exit must be close.
- What's to defend in a crypt?
- It's not just a crypt.
It's more like a stone circuit board.
This is the Matrix database.
CLARA: Database?
What do you mean. database?
- (WHISPERS) Oh.
- Oh?
- Oh.
Oh.
Looks like the primary service hatch.
- Just have to work out the key.
- Oh.
When Time Lords die. their minds are
uploaded to a thing called the Matrix.
This structure.
it's like a living computer.
It can predict the future.
Generate prophecies out of algorithms.
Ring the Cloister bells
in the event of impending catastrophe.
The Sliders. they're just like
the guard dogs. the firewall.
They're projections from
inside the Matrix itself.
The dead manning the battlements.
Was I supposed to
understand any of that?
The Time Lords have got a big computer
made of ghosts in a crypt
guarded by more ghosts.
- Didn't hurt. did it?
- Tiny bit.
Why would a computer need to protect
itself from the people who made it?
DOCTOR: All computers
do that in the end.
You wait till the internet starts.
Oh. that was a war.
GASTRON: They don't seem to be moving.
They're by lift shaft seven.
Keep monitoring.
Long time ago.
there was a student at the academy.
He'd got in here.
Disappeared for four days.
Showed up in a completely
different part of the city.
He said the Sliders talked to him.
They showed him the secret passage out.
We just need the code.
What. and the kid told you the secret?
Ah. no. He didn't tell anyone anything.
He went completely mad.
Never right in the head again.
so they say.
Okay. that's encouraging.
The last I heard.
he stole the moon
and the President's wife.
Was she. um...
Was she nice. the President's wife?
DOCTOR: Ah. well. that was a lie
put about by the Shabogans.
- (BEEPING)
- It was the President's daughter.
I didn't steal the moon. I lost...
I'd know you anywhere.
I was a completely different person
in those days.
Eccentric. A bit mad!
(CHUCKLES) Rude to people.
- Look at me again.
- I'm sorry. what?
In the eye. look at me. just do it.
What...
What is it?
How long has it been for you
since you last saw me?
Oh... (MUMBLES)
- Well. I'm not sure.
- How long?
I was stuck in a place.
- They...
- They?
What... Who... Who are we talking about?
They wanted something from me.
Information.
It really doesn't matter.
What happened to your coat?
Velvety one? I liked that one. It was...
It was very Doctor-ey...
- I changed it.
- Why?
Well. I can't be the Doctor
all the time.
(BEEPING)
I think I've almost got it.
I think this is it.
Tell me what they did to you.
Tell me what happened to the Doctor?
We're here.
Looks pretty quiet.
He seems to be talking to her.
Like he's telling her a story.
You might want to have a look.
Open up. We're going in.
We'll stick to the perimeter.
No more than three paces from the lift.
Do not enter the Cloisters.
DOCTOR: ...twenty feet of pure diamond.
Harder than diamond.
But you'll break through anything.
given time.
CLARA: How much time?
- FEMALE GENERAL: Miss Oswald.
- Stay back.
I'm sorry. But we have to find a way...
I said stay back!
The Hybrid. What is it?
What's so important
you would fight so long?
It doesn't matter what the Hybrid is.
It only matters that I
convinced them that I knew.
Otherwise. they would have kicked me out
and I'd have nothing left
to bargain with.
- What were you bargain for?
- What do you think?
(WHISPERS) You.
I had to find a way to save you.
I knew it had to be the Time Lords.
They cost you your life
on Trap Street. Clara.
And I was gonna make them
bring you back.
I just had to hang on
in there for a bit.
- How long?
- It was fine.
One question.
and you will answer.
How long was the Doctor trapped
inside the confession dial?
We think four-and-a-half billion years.
FEMALE GENERAL:
He could have left anytime he wanted.
He just had to say what he knew.
The dial would have released him.
(BEEPING)
(SOFTLY) Four-and-a-half billion years?
- If she says so.
- No.
Why would you even do that?
I was dead.
I was dead and gone. Why?
Why would you even
do that to yourself? (SIGHS)
I had a duty of care.
Listen. I'm nearly through here.
(BEEPING)
If I'm right. there should be
a service duct under here.
We'll be able to get
to the Old Workshops.
They'll have Tardises.
- (SNIFFS) Okay. listen.
- (HATCH DOOR OPENS)
I have something I need to say.
- We do not have time.
- No. my time...
My time is up. Doctor.
Between one heartbeat and the last
is all the time I have.
People like me and you.
we should say things to one another.
CLARA: And I'm gonna say them now.
You're monsters.
Here you are.
Hiding away at the end of time.
Do you even know why?
Because you are hated.
You are hated!
BY everybody.
But by nobody more than me.
- What did you say to him?
- (DOOR BEEPING)
Oh. nothing I'm gonna tell you.
Or anybody else.
Except maybe this one part.
I said...
"Don't worry. Doctor.
"They'll all be looking at me."
You need to tell us what
the Doctor is going to do now.
You really are thick. aren't you?
The Doctor is back on Gallifrey.
Took him four-and-a-half
billion years to get here.
What do you think he's gonna do now?
(WHOOSHING)
Well. he's stealing a Tardis
and running away.
Bye.
CLARA: You were quick!
Time machine. I backed up a bit.
OHILA:: Doctor. Doctor. face me!
Doctor. can you hear me?
Get out of that Tardis and face me. boy!
- Boy?
- (BEEPING)
OHILA: You have gone too far.
You have broken every code
you ever lived by.
After all this time.
after everything I've done.
don't you think the universe
owes me this?
Owes you what?
All you're doing is giving her hope?
Since when is hope a bad thing?
Hope is a terrible thing
on the scaffold.
(TARDIS WHOOSHING)
(GRUNTS)
FEMALE GENERAL: Where can he run?
Where he always runs.
Away.
Just away.
DOCTOR: What do you think
of the new wheels?
- Basic.
- Classic. Look at the colour scheme.
- (CHUCKLES) It's all white.
- Genius!
(THUD)
Check your heartbeat again.
- I think that you'll find you have one.
- Yeah?
It should've restarted when we broke
free of Gallifrey's time zone.
You're alive!
Now. we just have to shake off
the Time Lords.
There's only place we can do that.
What do say to lunch
followed by breakfast.
because we're time travellers
and that's how we roll?
Then cocktails with Moses.
Then I'm going to invent
a flying submarine. Why?
Because no one ever has.
and it's annoying!
And maybe we should use this Tardis
to find my proper one.
I need to change my shirt.
Doctor.
I still don't have a pulse.
Oh. you just haven't found it yet.
- Try again.
- I know how to take my pulse.
- (SIGHS)
- Look. I know how to do it.
See. no pulse. right?
- Uh-huh.
- (GLASSES WHIRRING)
Is it still there? Don't lie to me.
Uh. maybe we just have to fly
a little bit further.
Give it a bit more welly.
They said. your lot...
That if you save me. time would
fracture. What does that mean?
Ah. they were just exaggerating.
They exaggerate all the time.
History will be fine.
Time will heal. It always does.
- Always?
- Yeah.
It'll sort itself out.
It'll be all right.
You'll have a heartbeat.
Or don't you trust me any more?
No. Not when you're shouting.
- Where are we going?
- Nowhere in space.
Forward in time.
We're going to the last hours
of the universe.
We're going long past where
the Time Lords were hiding.
Literally. to the end.
They won't be able to track us there.
We’ll just be there for a minute.
I just need to...
I need to make an adjustment.
To what?
It's nothing. really. It's this...
A neural block?
Human compatible. that's what you said.
We don't have to stay here long.
Uh. check your heartbeat again.
Your timeline must have started by now.
Pulse. yeah?
You have a pulse. yes?
Pulse? Let me do it.
- I am checking it properly.
- This should work.
This has got to work.
CLARA: What if one last heartbeat
is all I've got.
What if time isn't healing?
What if the universe needs me to die?
The universe is over!
It doesn't have a say any more!
We're standing on the last ember.
The last fragment
of everything that ever was.
As of this moment.
I'm answerable to no one!
(SIGHS)
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
How can there be anybody there?
(KNOCKING CONTINUES)
Four knocks.
It's always four knocks.
No.
This one. I do alone.
What's out there?
Me.
(WHIRRING)
I told you once
so long ago
that the universe would become a very
small place when I'm angry with you.
Small enough for you yet?
Hello. me.
You don't seem surprised to see me.
DOCTOR: At the end of everything.
we should expect
the company of immortals.
so I've been told.
Even the other immortals are gone.
It's just me.
The one and only me.
Finally. you earned the title.
Sitting here in a reality bubble
at the end of time itself.
How are you sustaining it. by the way?
Brilliantly.
I've been watching stars die.
It was beautiful.
No.
It was sad.
It was both.
But that's not something
you would understand. is it?
You don't like endings.
She died. Doctor.
Clara died billions of years ago.
- You killed her.
- No.
- You let it happen.
- No. I didn't.
Neither did you.
She did.
She died for who she was
and for who she loved.
She fell where she stood. It was sad.
And it was beautiful.
And it is over.
We have no right to change who she was.
- Ashildr.
- Me.
Me. go to hell.
By my calculations.
you've got about five minutes.
You know why we run. Doctor?
Because it's fun.
Because we know
summer can't last forever.
Of course it can.
You just have to steal a time machine.
The Hybrid.
Five minutes to hell.
I think it's time to tell the truth.
(BEEPING)
Screen on.
ASHILDR: You were barely
more than a child.
You broke in here.
And the Wraith spoke to you
about the Hybrid.
Why did that story make you so scared?
DOCTOR: I don't know.
I don't remember everything.
(CHUCKLES) Sometimes you do.
It's always the way with things
we'd rather forget.
You remember now. though. don't you?
Tell me. Doctor. who is the Hybrid?
Who threatens all of time and space?
Oh. that's easy. That's very. very easy.
The Hybrid
is you.
ASHILDR: I'm human.
with a little bit of Mire inside me.
The Hybrid is supposed to be
half Time Lord. half Dalek.
DOCTOR: No. it isn't.
The actual prophecy specifies
only two warrior races.
The Daleks and the Time Lords
have made assumptions. of course.
And they would.
Humans and the Mire.
Both warrior races. it fits perfectly.
It's an interesting theory.
Do you have a better one?
By your own reasoning.
why couldn't the Hybrid be
half Time Lord. half human?
Tell me. Doctor. I've always wondered.
You're a Time Lord.
you're a highborn Gallifreyan.
Why is it you spend
so much time on Earth?
That's your best theory? I'm the Hybrid?
I've run away from Gallifrey
because I was afraid of myself?
It doesn't make any sense.
It makes perfect sense. and you know it.
Am I right?
Is it true?
Does it matter?
No.
Because I have a better theory.
Really?
What if the Hybrid
wasn't one person. but two?
- Two?
- A dangerous combination
of a passionate and powerful Time Lord
and a young woman
so very similar to him.
Companions who are willing to
push each other to extremes.
DOCTOR: She's my friend.
She's just my friend.
ASHILDR: How did you meet her?
Missy?
Missy.
Missy. the Master.
The lover of chaos.
Who wants you to love it. too.
She's quite the matchmaker.
Clara's my friend.
I know.
And you're willing to risk all of time
and space because you miss her.
One wonders what the pair of you
will get up to next.
Nothing. Nothing at all.
I know I went too far.
I get it.
That's why I'm doing what I'm doing.
And what would that be?
I'm taking her back to Earth.
Somewhere safe.
somewhere out of the way.
I'm going to wipe her memory
of every last detail of me.
It'll be like our friendship
never happened.
ASHILDR:
That may not be what she wants.
DOCTOR: I've done it before.
Usually. I do it telepathically.
But this time.
I've got something better.
It's quite painless.
Will you tell her
what you're going to do?
- Of course.
- When?
Now.
- Screen off.
- (MONITOR BEEPING)
You okay?
CLARA: Yeah.
Yeah. yeah. just. you know. my pulse.
Yeah. we'll fix that somehow. I promise.
You remember Ashildr. of course.
Yeah. sure.
I thought you'd be
more surprised to see her?
I was watching.
On the monitor.
(GASPS) No.
Doctor. whatever you're about to do.
don't do it.
It won't hurt. it'll be nothing.
- You will just pass out for a moment.
- And then?
- When you wake. you will be fine.
- But...
- Clara. just listen to me.
- Just say it.
Say it. Come on. tell me.
When you wake up.
you will have forgotten me.
You will have forgotten
we ever even met.
And why would I want that?
Because it's the only way.
That stuff in your head.
the image of me.
they could use it to find you.
I. uh... I used these.
- On what?
- That.
- What did you do?
- What do you think?
Ashildr's right. you see?
We're too alike.
- Tell me what you did.
- What else?
What else do you think I did?
I reversed the polarity.
Push that button. Doctor.
it will go off in your own face.
- Are you trying to trick me?
- What are you trying to do to me?
- I'm trying to keep you safe.
- Why?
Nobody's ever safe.
I've never asked you for that. ever.
These have been
the best years of my life.
And they are mine.
Tomorrow's promised to no one. Doctor.
but I insist upon my past.
I am entitled to that.
It's mine.
DOCTOR: Oh. Clara Oswald.
What am I doing?
You're right.
You're always...
Always right.
So what happens now? Eh?
Me and you. what do we do now?
I'm not sure you managed
to reverse the polarity.
I'm not even sure that you can.
It'll do something.
To one of us.
Better than flipping a coin.
Doctor...
You and me. together.
Look how far I went.
For fear of losing you.
This has to stop.
One of us has to go.
You really don't know which?
Let's find out.
Let's do it
like we've done everything else...
Together.
How about we just don't?
Why don't we just fly away somewhere?
- Oh. that'd be great. wouldn't it?
- (BOTH CHUCKLE)
God. yeah.
(LAUGHS)
Good luck. Clara.
Good luck. Doctor.
(BEEPING)
So. what happens now?
I suppose we just. um...
We just wait a minute. I suppose.
One of us...
I don't think I could ever forget you.
Clara. I don't think
you're ever gonna have to.
(GASPS)
No.
- Run like hell.
- What?
Run like hell
because you always need to.
Laugh at everything
because it's always funny.
No. Stop it. You're saying goodbye.
Don't say goodbye.
Never be cruel and never be cowardly.
And if you ever are. always make amends.
- (GASPS)
- Stop it!
Stop this... Stop it!
Never eat pears. They're too squishy.
And they always make your chin wet.
That one is quite important.
write it down.
I didn't mean to do this. I'm sorry.
It's okay. (GROANS)
It's okay.
I went too far.
I broke all my own rules.
I became the Hybrid.
This is right!
(BREATHING HEAVILY)
I accept it.
I can't.
There has to be something I can do.
Smile for me.
Go on. Clara Oswald.
One last time.
How could I smile?
It's okay.
Don't you worry.
(SOFTLY) I'll remember you.
Sir.
Are you all right?
Where am I?
How did I get here?
Clara asked me to look after you.
She said you might be a bit upset.
- Clara?
- Yeah.
She was just here.
I don't know where she went.
Clara?
Clara. who?
When something goes missing. you can
always recreate it by the hole it left.
I know her name was Clara.
I know we travelled together.
I know that there was an Ice Warrior
on a submarine
and a Mummy on the Orient Express.
I know we sat together in the Cloisters
and she told me something
very important.
but I've no idea what she said.
Or what she looked like.
Or how she talked.
Or laughed.
There's nothing there.
Just nothing.
Are you looking for her?
I'm trying. (SIGHS)
She could be anyone. right?
You don't know
who you're looking for. I mean...
She could be me. for all you know.
There's one thing I know about her.
just one thing.
If I met her again.
I'd absolutely know her.
I think that we were here. you know.
I think that we were here together once.
I'm sure I remember.
Over here.
Stupid...
Amy and Rory. It was Amy and Rory.
What about your Tardis. eh?
- You found that yet?
- No.
Somebody's moved it from London.
I'm still looking.
But this diner...
It wasn't always here. was it?
It used to be
on the other side of the hill.
Maybe someone will
find your Tardis for you.
(GUITAR STRUMMING)
What Clara told you in the Cloisters...
I don't remember
a single thing about it.
You said. "Memories...
"...become stories when we forget them."
Maybe some of them become songs.
(GUITAR STRUMMING)
That'd be nice.
Yeah. it would be. wouldn't it?
(TARDIS WHOOSHING)
(WIND WHISTLING)
ASHILDR: I don't think
I've got the chameleon circuit working.
The outer shell might be stuck
as an American diner.
Awesome.
Still no pulse?
(SNIFFS)
Time isn't healing. I'm still frozen.
You know what that means?
It means my death is a fixed event.
The universe depends on it happening.
I'm sorry.
Why?
Why does everybody think I am so scared?
We all face the Raven in the end.
That is the deal.
If I go back to Gallifrey.
they can put me back. right?
On Trap Street.
the moment they took me out?
Of course.
Mind you.
Seeing as I'm not actually ageing.
there's still a tiny
little bit of wiggle room. isn't there?
- Wiggle room?
- Wiggle room. yeah.
You know. wiggle room.
We could. um. you know.
stop off on the way.
- Where are we going?
- Gallifrey.
Like I said...
Gallifrey.
(TARDIS WHOOSHING)
The long way round.
(TARDIS POWERING UP)
(WHIRRING)
(TARDIS WHOOSHING)
(THEME MUSIC PLAYING)
Ripped By mstoll
Happy New Year 2016 - New Year. New Color ;-)
(KNOCKING ON DOOR)
Is there anything on my head?
Erm... Well. yes.
- River!
- Death initiating.
Stop holding my hand.
People don't do that to me.
Destroy them!
RIVER: Nobody move! Or the head gets it.
Sonic Trowel? Do you realise
how ridiculous that sounds?
- You planned to take my head?
- Never crossed my mind.
Long live the King.
RIVER: This is a serious mission.
There is nothing to laugh about here.
We're being threatened by a bag!
Give us the treasure!